Hello, and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan, and today
we're going to be practicing how to
identify cis and trans alkenes, and
also going through some naming of
them, um, in this particular video.
So the first thing is, let's just start
with the fundamentals, is how can you
identify when you have a cis trans alkene?
The whole idea with this is a simple
trick that how I always view these,
is you're going to be looking exactly
at the double bond and pretending that
it's like a set of railroad tracks.
So when I have this little double bond
here, what I always do is I draw in my
head, or if you want to on your paper,
is a little set of dashed lines, and
you're going to be pretending that that
double bond is a little railroad track.
Now what you need to do to determine
if they're cis or trans is you're
looking to see if there are different
groups on each side of the double bond.
So for example, if I look at the
CH3s here, We see that both of these
are on the same side at the moment.
So whenever we have them both on
the upper or both on the lower
together, this is referred to as sys.
Okay, so sys, same.
And the entire idea here is that whenever
you have these differences, you need
to have on each end, there needs to
be two completely different groups.
So you can see that I have like
the methyl, and I also have the
hydrogen on the left, they're
both different from each other.
So it needs to be different
on both sides here.
Now, both of them are together.
So this is for the methyls.
So this is referred to as cis.
Now, if I go to another one,
well, what would be the other?
Well, if I have cis, then I also have
trans and I do the same little idea.
I look and I draw my little dashes
and then I see that, Ooh, okay.
I can have my methyl that one
of them is on the top and then
the other one is on the bottom.
So we have them on opposite
sides of my railroad track.
Now in this case, whenever they are
opposite, this is referred to as trans.
So whenever it comes to trying to identify
these different structures, We still
follow the same normal naming conventions.
We named the longest chain, just like
we would do for any alkane, however,
or alkene, but we need to make sure
we include that cis trans in the name.
So for example, I have four carbons along
my longest stretch of my chain here.
So the way that you would name this
one is you would say trans to tell
you about this isomer here, right?
That says that we have this three
dimensional shape around this molecule.
And the way we would number
this, we'd say trans 2 butene.
Now for the next one, the way
you would name it as well, you
might be able to kind of guess it.
Well, if the other one is cis, the other
one would be cis 2 butene for the name.
Okay?
So each one of them says their
particular geometry around it.
Now why is that the case?
Well, the thing to keep in
mind is the double bond has a
trigonal planar geometry to it.
And because of the double bond, it
actually is stuck in that entire geometry.
You can't just simply rotate it without
breaking the bond in the process.
So, you know, if you rotate the whole
molecule, those different groups
are always going to be pointing in
the, always going to be opposite of
each other no matter what, unless
you break the bond or force it to
go through a chemical reaction.
So So that's the most important thing
about these is that even if I end up
rotating all these different structures,
they are always going to be stuck in
that cis or trans unless you go make
it go through an actual reaction.
So let's take a look at a bunch of
examples of this practicing identifying
sister trans and going through our naming.
All right.
So for the following problem, we're
going to be naming and identifying the
different So with this, the whole idea
first is we need to just go through
each example and let's try to see if
we can figure out if it's cis or trans.
And then we're going to
feed that into its name.
So the first thing is I'm going to draw
my little railroad tracks just like I
did in the introduction of this video.
So what we're looking at is are the
different groups, are they on the same
side or are they on different sides?
And it doesn't have to only be methyl
groups, it can be anything as long
as it's different carbon groups.
halogens, as long as you see them,
are they together or the opposite?
So we see both these chlorines, they're
both together, so being that they
are the same, that refers to as cis.
So what we would do for the naming
is we'd first start by writing that
down, so we'd have cis in the name.
Now the next part is going to be
naming and numbering our different
groups, which are our chlorines here.
We have two of them, so we've got
to number our, our molecule here,
They're gonna be at one and two.
We'll put a dash.
So one, two, and being that there
are multiple, we'll say die and then
we will finish it with di Chloro.
And then being that we had two carbons,
it's gonna be di chloro ethene for the e
and e ending to denote the double bond.
Keep that in mind, right?
We gotta make sure we do include
that ending when we are doing these.
Don't accidentally put alkane endings.
It's really easy to do that, especially
when you're first learning all this stuff.
Okay.
Now, if we were to do the next one,
same idea here is we're going to
be looking at the different groups.
So we see that we have two different ones.
They don't have to be the same as long
as you're seeing are they opposite?
Are they together?
In this case, when I look at my
little railroad track, I see that
they are both opposites of each other.
So what that means is they
are going to be trans.
So when it comes to us naming,
we're going to say trans.
And from there we're going
to number and name all these.
So how do I decide the numbering here?
Well, being that you have
two halogen, you gotta go off
electro negativity for the order.
Chlorine is a higher electro negativity,
so that's gonna get the number one spot.
Then from there, what we're gonna do
is we're going to, uh, alphabetize
how they're written in the name.
This can be trans to bromo.
Then one chloro.
And then we'll finish that
name with the ethene part.
So I'm going to write that
underneath because I kind of
ran out of room on myself.
So it'd be trans 2 bromo 1 chloro
ethene would be its entire name.
Let's try to do another.
So with this one, is it cis or trans?
That's just the entire idea.
So what we need to look at is if you
notice on the left side of this molecule,
so if I look over here we can see that we
have a hydrogen and then another hydrogen.
They're both on the exact same side.
How can you tell the difference
between these two hydrogens?
And you'll think, well, I can't, right?
They're the exact same thing.
So what that means is, well, even though I
have that fluorine, it's gonna be neither.
So you just read it like
a normal molecule, right?
We can still go through numbering it
and we could still just say one fluoro
Athene would be the name of this molecule.
So just like you would name any normal
alkene, they don't all have cis or trans.
The only double bonds that do are
when you have unique groups on
both sides of that double bond.
Okay.
Same idea here is let's do the idea.
So I did as a skeletal structure here.
So these are a little bit trickier, right?
Cause you got to actually remember that
there are hydrogens that are hidden.
Um, they're not being showed.
They're always assumed.
So if you think of like the one on
the left, right, even though they're
not here, there are two hydrogens
that are in existence, right?
There needs to be four bonds
on every single carbon.
So what does that mean if I look at that?
Well, I have the same
groups on the left, right?
They're both hydrogens.
But the other thing is I also have
two of the same groups on the other
side, What are each of the ends here?
These are CH3s.
So these are identical as
well, so they're no different.
So meaning that when we see this, it has
neither, it has nothing, it has no cis or
trans, it's just a normal, uh, structure.
So how would we go through
numbering this, right?
So we go one, two, and three, so
therefore making it 2 methylpentene
would be my name, or not pentene,
propene would be my name, okay?
Let's do a couple more,
and then we'll be done.
So now this next one, same idea as
before, we want to name and number it and
then look at all the different groups.
Now with these guys, when it
comes to cis or trans, these are
something that you cannot actually
label with the cis or trans system.
Um, if you're someone that's taking this
as an organic chemistry major, this is
where E and Z notation would come from.
This is something that is
not covered in my course.
That's for more for
allied health students.
where you're trying to assign
priority to everything.
So in this case, there's no
exact way for you to tell
what's the most important thing.
You can say that the chlorines
are opposite of each other.
So there could be an argument that
could be made to say that this is trans.
Same thing with the carbon groups
being opposite of each other.
However, I think it's more appropriate to
say that you can't really label this one.
It would be better to use a
different notation for this.
So we're just going to go through and
just name, practice, name your alkene,
and we're going to say, we're going to do
kind of like neither, but we're going to
put a little asterisk next to it that you
could say cis or trans, but I would say
it probably be better not to, um, without
doing a priority based naming system.
So with this guy, right, when we were
trying to name it, so I kind of like
numbered it a little bit off, right?
So we'd say it'd be one over here on
the methyl, and we have number two.
And then we'd have 3, 4, and 5, right?
So we would just kind of shift
all of our numbers down, right?
We want to make sure we have
that longest continuous chain.
It's really easy to forget that when you
are dealing with these kinds of molecules.
So what we would have is we
have 2, 3, dichlorohexene
in this case.
So we number where those dichloros are.
Now the only difference here is you want
to number where the double bond starts,
which is on carbon number 2 in this case.
I would say two, three,
dichloro, two, ene, right?
And notice how it's not
always sister trans.
Sometimes it is, sometimes it's not,
but for example, here, as I picked two
examples, that's drawing them as skeletal
structures, being that this is a really
common thing that many of you will have to
do, um, when you're drawing them, so you
kind of see that on the top here, We can
follow our zigzag when it comes to trans.
So if I kind of like imagine my
little dot dotted line down this,
we have one group that's pointing
down, the other group pointing up.
So it's like kind of like if you
look at it and you can rotate this
molecule, you can kind of see the
trans shape a little bit better, right?
So if you were trying to number this,
you would go one, two, three, four, five.
So what would that end up being is
that would be trans two and teen
would be the name of the structure.
Now the other one that's right below
it, this is Sys to Pentene as the
other one, and you can see that if
I kind of once again draw my little
line down the center, notice that I
have one group pointing up, and then
the other one pointing up as well.
And they could also be flipped, where they
could be both be pointing down, keep that
in mind, Sys can be, they're going to be
making that little U shape, whether it's
pointing down, you know, or it's going up.
And that's really the ultimate idea here
when you're looking at these structures.
Okay, so this was a little bit, this was
a lot more than I expected for this video,
but I hope that it helped a little kind
of going through how to identify them,
how to name them, and going through and
letting you see different examples of
how you can draw and write these as well.
And that's going to be what the follow up
video for this is, is how to actually draw
these in their different representations.
The most important thing is being able
to show that 3D structure of the double
bond, so that we can show cis and trans.
Okay, thank you so much for listening.
If this is your first time
here, thank you for being, uh,
being here in this community.
And please hit that like subscribe
button if you hadn't been before.
And thank you so much.
And I hope to see you again in the future.
Bye now.